<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-02T16:00:49-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jacob Varner’s Basketball Blog</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Home-and-home series I want to see each SEC basketball team schedule for next season or in the coming years</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/30/home-and-home-series-I-want-to-see-each-sec-basketball-team-schedule-next-season-or-in-the-coming-years.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Home-and-home series I want to see each SEC basketball team schedule for next season or in the coming years" /><published>2020-04-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-04-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/30/home-and-home-series-I-want-to-see-each-sec-basketball-team-schedule-next-season-or-in-the-coming-years</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/30/home-and-home-series-I-want-to-see-each-sec-basketball-team-schedule-next-season-or-in-the-coming-years.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the best things about college basketball are the atmospheres at most games, especially big games that aren’t very common. There can certainly be great atmospheres for neutral site games, but nothing quite beats home crowds when a teams from different conferences schedule home-and-home series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s two big schools and strong programs playing each other on both home courts or even smaller schools getting the chance to host bigger programs with a rare shot at a major upset on their home court, the atmospheres rarely disappoint in a home-and-home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As non-conference schedules are starting to come together for SEC basketball teams, it seemed like a good time to fantasize about which home-and-home series I would like each team to schedule for next season or the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While next season might not be the best year for long distance travel I still hope things return to “normal” eventually and some of these series are more realistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, before I begin, if you’d like to check out who already is scheduled for each SEC basketball team so far, I’ve been trying to keep track of all schedule announcements for the next few years on the &lt;a href=&quot;/resources.html&quot;&gt;resources page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;alabama-vs-uab&quot;&gt;Alabama vs UAB&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been pushing for Alabama to start up a home-and-home with the Blazers since Auburn re-started their series with them a few years ago. UAB hiring Andy Kennedy this off-season only makes me want this home-and-home even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alabama has only played UAB once before, where the Blazers defeated the Crimson Tide 58-56 in a 1993 NIT game hosted in Tuscaloosa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;arkansas-vs-ucla&quot;&gt;Arkansas vs UCLA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My logic for this one is that both programs are currently working to get back to their better days and both are doing so with two coaches entering their second year at each school. Cronin has quite a bit of experience on Musselman, but it would be nice to see whether Cronin’s slower pace, defensive minded scheme or Musselman’s uptempo, high scoring system would prevail with both coaches still trying to fully implement their systems at new schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A home-and-home series would also be the first time the two teams have faced each other since UCLA prevented Arkansas from winning back to back titles by defeating them in the 1995 National Championship game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arkansas has only faced the Bruins three times: a National Title loss in 1995, a Reginal Semifinal win in 1978, and a road blowout in 1973.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;auburn-vs-texas&quot;&gt;Auburn vs Texas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a totally selfish pick as a recent Auburn grad that moved to Austin, TX, but I still believe it would be a fun matchup and I bet I’m not the only one that would like to see this home-and-home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Texas landing top 10 prospect Greg Brown over Auburn recently, a series starting next year would be ideal, but that’s probably not likely since the Longhorns already have games with Gonzaga and Villanova booked for next season in a year where Shaka Smart’s job is on the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn is 1-1 vs the Longhorns, but the two haven’t faced each other since 1955.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;florida-vs-villanova&quot;&gt;Florida vs Villanova&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we’re being honest, I just want any SEC team to schedule a home-and-home with Villanova. I also think both schools have a dominant recent history with Villanova’s run under Jay Wright being very similar to Florida’s run under Billy Donovan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both programs have two wins in the four games that they have played with the last game being a Florida victory to advance to the 2006 Final Four where the Gators would eventually win their first of back-to-back National Championships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;georgia-vs&quot;&gt;Georgia vs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kentucky-vs-indiana&quot;&gt;Kentucky vs Indiana&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure John Calipari is allergic to scheduling home-and-home series, but if he’s going to schedule any, I think this would be the best one. The two programs have not been able to come to an agreement on another matchup since the last regular season game between the two where Indiana knocked off top ranked Kentucky with a buzzer beating three in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could probably come up with a pretty long list of home-and-home series I want to see just involving Kentucky, but honestly I’ll take anything other than the almost annual match-ups with other blue bloods on neutral courts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lsu-vs&quot;&gt;LSU vs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ole-miss-vs&quot;&gt;Ole Miss vs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mississippi-state-vs&quot;&gt;Mississippi State vs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;missouri-vs&quot;&gt;Missouri vs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;south-carolina-vs-kansas-state&quot;&gt;South Carolina vs Kansas State&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s finally time that Frank Martin makes a return to Manhattan, KS and faces his former team. Martin departed Kansas State to take the South Carolina job in 2012 despite never losing less than 21 games with the Wildcats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Currie isn’t at Kansas State anymore, so that potential storyline isn’t a factor anymore, but the two programs have still only had one meeting all time. South Carolina beat Kansas State by two on a neutral court in 1989.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another potential Big 12/SEC Challenge match-up, but I’d like to see a true home-and-home scheduled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tennessee-vs&quot;&gt;Tennessee vs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;texas-am-vs&quot;&gt;Texas A&amp;amp;M vs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vanderbilt-vs-harvard&quot;&gt;Vanderbilt vs Harvard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who doesn’t like watching smart kids go against even smarter kids in basketball? This one is pretty random, but the two programs have only faced each other twice all time and the most recent matchup was in the 2012 NCAA Tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vanderbilt is 2-0 all time against the Crimson, but now might be the chance for Harvard to get their first win in the series before Jerry Stackhouse potentially gets Vanderbilt back to winning ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an added bonus, Harvard currently plays in the second oldest active venue while Memorial Gym has it’s own history spanning more than 65 years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Varner</name></author><category term="SEC" /><summary type="html">One of the best things about college basketball are the atmospheres at most games, especially big games that aren’t very common. There can certainly be great atmospheres for neutral site games, but nothing quite beats home crowds when a teams from different conferences schedule home-and-home series.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A look back at SEC basketball in the 2000s - total wins, conference wins, and tournament success</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/27/a-look-back-at-sec-basketball-in-the-2000s.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A look back at SEC basketball in the 2000s - total wins, conference wins, and tournament success" /><published>2020-04-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-04-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/27/a-look-back-at-sec-basketball-in-the-2000s</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/27/a-look-back-at-sec-basketball-in-the-2000s.html">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, Blake Lovell tweeted out a few interesting stats from the past few years in the SEC:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;tweet-wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Random SEC basketball stats thread for those who get bored in the offseason. Let’s start with the top seven teams in overall wins the past five seasons:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;UK - 140&lt;br /&gt;Auburn - 110&lt;br /&gt;Florida - 108&lt;br /&gt;Tennessee - 105&lt;br /&gt;Arkansas - 103&lt;br /&gt;South Carolina - 102&lt;br /&gt;Miss St - 98&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Blake Lovell (@theblakelovell) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/theblakelovell/status/1250475079269584899?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 15, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That gave me the idea to take it even further and look at similar stats for all of the 2000s. There were already interesting observations in his original thread, and I figured there would be other trends when I extended it all the way back to the 1999-2000 season and I’d like to think I was right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back and looked at regular season wins, conference wins, SEC tournament wins, NCAA Tournament wins, and all postseason appearances. I originally planned to use some more creative graphics to convey the data, but most things got pretty convoluted, so I opted to just use basic charts with shades of red/green to show most of the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regular-season-wins&quot;&gt;Regular Season Wins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first and most obvious measure of success over time is regular season wins. While regular season wins certainly don’t perfectly reflect strength of schedule for each team, it’s interesting to see the ups and downs for each team throughout the millennium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each season has it’s own color scale where the lowest amount of wins is in the darkest red while the most wins is darkest green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-4-27/Image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;SEC Basketball Regular Season Wins Each Year from 2000 to 2020&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that I noticed is that really only Kentucky and Florida have had consistent success throughout the last 20 years with the Gators’ worst year being 15 wins and the Wildcats’ worst year being just 18 wins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alabama’s consistency has been very impressive by getting between 16-18 wins in the regular season 11 out of the 21 years, including each of the last 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last three years for Vanderbilt have really counteracted the success from 2007-2012 and have pulled the average down more than a full win compared to the first 18 years of the 2000s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the success of the last 3 to 4 years for Auburn has started to salvage abysmal records throughout most of the time period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-4-27/Image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ranking SEC Basketball Teams By Regular Season Wins Over the Last 5 Years 10 Years and Since 2000 Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reign at the top for Kentucky and Florida is more apparent when looking at the totals over the last 5, 10, and 21 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also of note, Arkansas has quietly had quite a bit of success in the regular season as they jump from 8th in overall wins since 2000 to 3rd and 4th over the last 10 and 5 years respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only teams to trend up over the three samples are Auburn and South Carolina while the only teams to trend down over the three samples are Alabama, Florida, Missouri, and Vanderbilt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Alabama’s consistency was pretty apparent with almost identical amounts of wins in more years, when looking at the average wins per year over the three sample time frames, LSU is also very consistent with just 17.8, 17.8, and then 18.4 wins per year as the time frame shrinks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regular-season-conference-wins&quot;&gt;Regular Season Conference Wins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While regular season wins are a good indicator for all the teams, including Missouri and Texas A&amp;amp;M before they joined the SEC, it’s better to compare the SEC teams against each other directly by looking at conference wins over the same period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-4-27/Image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;SEC Basketball Regular Season Conference Wins Each Year from 2000 to 2020&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the observations from the regular season wins overall hold true for conference wins as well. Kentucky and Florida are still at the top and Alabama is still very consistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anything, Kentucky’s dominance is even more apparent when looking at just conference wins. The Wildcats had or tied for the most wins in the conference 10 of the 21 years and never finished below 0.500 in the SEC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vanderbilt is the only team to go winless since 2000, but LSU makes up 3 of the 8 2-win conference seasons in the same time period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-4-27/Image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ranking SEC Basketball Teams By Regular Season Conference Wins Over the Last 5 Years 10 Years and Since 2000 Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kentucky has had a nice amount of wins over the last five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;South Carolina has had even more success in conference games than the season overall which is good for third most wins in the SEC over the last five years including a 29 win improvement compared to the previous five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn also has more wins in the last three years than they had in the 7 years before that combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the 3 good recent years, Auburn still has less SEC wins over the last 10 years than Texas A&amp;amp;M does, despite the Aggies only being in the SEC for 8 of those years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-tournament-wins&quot;&gt;SEC Tournament Wins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the SEC Tournament byes and now double-byes, this chart isn’t the best indication of overall success in the tournament, but it still indicates the winners (in bold) and can give a sense of which teams show up in a comparable tournament scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also didn’t include any wins from the very brief 2020 SEC Tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-4-27/Image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;SEC Tournament Wins Each Year From 2000 to 2019&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC Tournament has not been kind to Arkansas, Auburn, Ole Miss, South Carolina, or Vanderbilt as each team has gone winless in 10 or more seasons over the last 20 SEC Tournaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last 20 years, there have only been 8 unique SEC Tournament winners with Kentucky taking home 9 titles, Florida winning 4, Mississippi State with 2, and then Arkansas, Auburn, Georgia, Ole Miss, and Vanderbilt each winning once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By almost always getting at least one win, Alabama has managed to be in the top 5 for total SEC Tournament wins in each of the 3 time periods, despite also never winning more than 2 games since 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-4-27/Image6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ranking SEC Tournament Wins Over the Last 5 Years 10 Years and Since 2000 Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn has been boom or bust over the last decade. The Tigers finished 8 of those years without a win but then won the entire tournament in 2019 and strung together 3 wins in 2015. However, those 7 wins are still good enough for a distant second place over the last 5 years while Kentucky has 13 in the same time period, including 4 titles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, Kentucky’s dominance at the SEC Tournament has been even more so than their general dominance in regular season results as they have 10 more wins at the SEC tournament than everyone else over the last 10 years and since 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I was making a guess before gathering all of this data, I definitely would not have had Mississippi state as the team with the third most SEC Tournament wins since 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ncaa-tournament-wins&quot;&gt;NCAA Tournament Wins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at NCAA Tournament wins over the years is a good way to not only compare teams within the SEC, but also show which years the SEC has been successful as a conference overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-4-27/Image7.png&quot; alt=&quot;SEC Basketball NCAA Tournament Wins Each Year from 2000 to 2019&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the 2000 NCAA Tournament, the SEC has won 3 titles and made 11 total Final Fours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite sending the 8 teams to the 2018 NCAA Tournament, the SEC still only had 8 wins overall and didn’t send any teams past the Sweet 16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arkansas, Georgia, and Mississippi State are the only schools to not win multiple games in a single NCAA Tournament since 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;South Carolina has zero wins in the NCAA Tournament since 2000 outside of their 2017 run to the Final Four.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-4-27/Image8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ranking SEC Basketball Teams By NCAA Tournament Wins Over the Last 5 Years 10 Years and Since 2000 Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Georgia has the worst record since 2000 with just one win overall and no wins in the last 10 years&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Missouri has no NCAA Tournament wins since moving to the SEC in 2013 despite having the 9 wins since 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Florida has at least one NCAA Tournament in 13 of the past 20 years while Kentucky has at least one NCAA Tournament win in 17 of the last 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;postseason-status&quot;&gt;Postseason Status&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While wins in the NCAA Tournament are the best sign of success, just getting to the NCAA Tournament or a postseason tournament at all is see as a success for just about every team in the conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-4-27/Image9.png&quot; alt=&quot;SEC Basketball Postseason Status Each Year from 2000 to 2019&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kentucky is the only team to make it to the postseason every year since 2000 and the Wildcats only went to the NIT in 2009 and 2013. Florida has similar success with the Gators only missing the postseason in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn had the longest postseason drought by not qualifying for any postseason tournament from 2010 to 2017. An NIT appearance in 2009 prevented that from being an even longer drought from 2004 to 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with that drought, Auburn also has the most seasons where they have failed to reach the postseason with 14 in the past 20 years. South Carolina also missed the postseason 12 years our of the last 20 and Arkansas had 10 years with no postseason play to show for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alabama has the most NIT appearances in with 8 while Ole Miss is close behind with 7 NIT trips in the last 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only 4 SEC teams (Auburn, Florida, Kentucky, and Tennessee) currently have active NCAA Tournament streaks of more than one year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-4-27/Image10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ranking SEC Basketball Teams By Postseason Status Over the Last 5 Years 10 Years and Since 2000 Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to use 4, 2, and 1 as indicators for the postseason tournament that each team qualified for each year so that the averages would better reflect the success overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kentucky and Florida are clearly regular NCAA Tournament teams with them averaging 3.8 and 3.5 points respectively over the last 20 years. Several teams average out to be NIT teams over the last 20 years&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was mostly just an excuse for me to go back and look at historical stats while there are no real sports going on, but it was a nice way to gather the data and look at the trends for success (and lack thereof) for each of the SEC teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to look at data since 2000 because I think it’s a large enough window to show ups and downs for most teams, but also recent enough to be more reflective of modern basketball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I feel like when success is measured across multiple decades, it tends to favor programs like Kentucky even more because a winning program in the beginning was able to build much more momentum and success overall due to the share of resources and talent they had in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking just at the last 20ish years certainly still shows that Kentucky is a dominant program and the gold standard of the SEC, but all programs should be on a much more level playing field for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already have a plan to go back and compare teams based on all time wins, tournament appearances, Final Fours, draft picks, and other “indicators of program success,” but that might take me a little longer to gather the information in one place in order to continue to make fun charts and graphics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Black Lovell’s original inspiration for this, I’m just hoping that I can keep myself entertained in the absence of real basketball content and as a result, I plan to pass some of that entertainment onto others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading, and feel free to let me know &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitter.com/jacobvarner&quot;&gt;on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; if you notice other trends or things that stand out to you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Varner</name></author><category term="SEC" /><category term="History" /><summary type="html">A few weeks ago, Blake Lovell tweeted out a few interesting stats from the past few years in the SEC:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">With 200 days left until college basketball returns these are the biggest questions for each SEC team</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/24/with-200-days-until-college-basketball-returns-these-are-the-biggest-questions-for-each-sec-basketball-team.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="With 200 days left until college basketball returns these are the biggest questions for each SEC team" /><published>2020-04-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-04-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/24/with-200-days-until-college-basketball-returns-these-are-the-biggest-questions-for-each-sec-basketball-team</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/24/with-200-days-until-college-basketball-returns-these-are-the-biggest-questions-for-each-sec-basketball-team.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s that time of year where almost every college basketball writer is putting out their “way too early pre-season polls and rankings” and there has already been quite a bit of information to inform these decisions. However, with 200 days until the season starts (if it starts on time, fingers crossed) there are still quite a few decisions left to be made and many of them will have a decent impact on SEC basketball for the 2020-2021 season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m withholding my formal predictions for next year until more things fall into place, because I still think it is too far out and there are too many things left to decide. With that said, these are the main questions I am waiting to have answered regarding each of the SEC basketball teams and how I think each decision/outcome can affect next basketball season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest question of them all, and I’ll go ahead and get it out of the way, is how COVID-19 and the cautionary restrictions it has required so far will affect the 2020-2021 basketball season. I’m writing this post on the assumption that everything will start on time, but it has already had and will continue to have an impact on development for all teams, which I will try to keep in mind when forming my opinions and preparing for next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of that, these are the biggest decisions left to be made and questions I’m waiting to have answered for each SEC basketball team as we are still 200 days away from tip-off of the next college basketball season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;alabama-crimson-tide&quot;&gt;Alabama Crimson Tide&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alabama, and 2nd year head coach Nate Oats, have already made a splash in the last few weeks by picking up big commitments from key high school prospects and important transfers. As I write this, Alabama has already signed three 4-star high school prospects, the 3rd overall JUCO prospect, and a key grad transfer in Jordan Bruner. Former 5-star guard Jahvon Quinerly who transferred from Villanova will also be eligible while two other player return from injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, there are eight newcomers for the Crimson Tide next season, but with a 2nd year head coach trying to implement a new uptempo system, that might be better than usual for teams bringing in several newcomers. Kira Lewis, arguably the best player on Alabama’s roster last season, and certainly the most important, has already announced that he is staying in the draft, and this will be a major blow for the Crimson Tide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than Kira Lewis, there are two other key players tha have already declared for the NBA Draft in John Petty and Herbert Jones. To me, the decision to stay in the NBA Draft or return from both of these guys is the biggest question mark regarding Alabama basketball next season. There is currently only one scholarship spot remaining, so as it stands, only one of the two could remove their name from the draft right now, but even if both remove their names, I’m sure Nate Oats will find a spot on the 2020-2021 roster, even if it means someone else transfers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With either back, Alabama is definitely a contender at the top of the SEC next season, but if both join Kira Lewis in staying in the NBA Draft, I’m not sure I buy into Alabama making such a large jump next season. I think another year with Nate Oats’ new system will lead to an improvement regardless, given the players being added next season, but the decision of these two guys will decide the ceiling and overall success of next season’s team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;arkansas-razorbacks&quot;&gt;Arkansas Razorbacks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section is going to sound very repetitive, because honestly, I see Arkansas in almost the exact same boat as Alabama right now. Both programs have a quality coach going into year two, both programs have signed an impressive class of newcomers including a mix of 4-star high school prospects and key transfers, and both schools are waiting to see if their stars are going to stay in the NBA Draft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Isaiah Joe and Mason Jones have entered their name into the NBA Draft, and like Alabama, there is just currently one roster spot remaining for either to return without another player having to transfer or give up their scholarship in some way. I’m trying not to sound repetitive, but again, who decides to return to Arkansas is the biggest question mark I still have for next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isaiah Joe was a key player who missed some key games in the middle of conference play and as a result Arkansas lost every game he missed. Mason Jones had nine 30+ games, including two 40+ games, and was the guy on the court that kept the Razorbacks in every single game. One of these guys will likely return for another season in Fayetteville, and whoever it is will make a big difference on next year’s team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Alabama, if both return, Arkansas is an easy contender at the top of the SEC, and if both decide to stay in the draft, they’ll still be fine, but probably not a contender. I tend to think that the newcomers that are coming in for Arkansas are a tad bit better than at Alabama, but the Razorbacks also lose more contributors to graduation, especially Jimmy Whitt who played the most minutes for Arkansas last season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;auburn-tigers&quot;&gt;Auburn Tigers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn loses five scholarship players to graduation and Isaac Okoro to the NBA Draft, which is somehow even more than they lost last season. Bruce Pearl proved people wrong and made noise with a “depleted” team last season, but this will arguably be a bigger challenge. So far, the Tigers have reloaded quite well with the best recruiting class in program history including 5-star Sharife Cooper and three other 3/4-stars. It’ll be another big challenge to reload, but with the promise the freshman class showed, plus Bruce Pearl at the helm, Auburn should be fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, “fine” probably won’t cut it for the new expectations of Auburn basketball. That being said, there are still two more spots left on next year’s team, and who fills those two spots is the biggest question remaining for Auburn. The Tigers missed out on top 10 prospects Jalen Green, who opted for the G League, and Greg Brown, who chose to stay home and play for Texas, but there are still quality players that have the option of playing for Auburn next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn needs size desperately with Austin Wiley and Anfernee McLemore graduating, so that will likely be addressed by one of the remaining roster spots. Auburn has already been mentioned as a finalist for the top player in the 2021 class who is expected to reclassify to 2020, but as with the other top prospects from 2020, there certainly isn’t a guarantee that Auburn lands Jonathan Kuminga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously with Kuminga (or some other highly rated recruit) Auburn would get enough talent to reload and compete for the SEC once again, but as long as they get another big body that’s needed in some form or another, Bruce Pearl has proven that he shouldn’t ever be underestimated. The last two spots on Auburn’s roster could decide whether the Tigers are an SEC favorite or will be competing just to make the NCAA tournament next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;florida-gators&quot;&gt;Florida Gators&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Florida is only losing Kerry Blackshear to graduation and Dontay Bassett who is transferring the Weber State. The Gators have been fortunate to have both Scottie Lewis, a former 5-star prospect, and Keyontae Johnson announce that they are returning for next season. They have added two 4-star prospects out of high school and the fifth overall JUCO prospect as well as two transfers that will be available next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Nembhard could still potentially make the decision to declare for the NBA Draft, but with the deadline quickly approaching, it looks like he might opt to stay for his Junior season. With Nembhard there are no more roster spots remaining for next season, so his decision is probably the biggest decision left for Florida and if he goes, whoever Mike White gets to replace him will also be very important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a bonus question I have for Florida next season, I’m wondering what Mike White will do to capitalize on the talent going into next season, especially if Nembhard returns. Last season, Florida was regularly considered a top 5-10 team by ahead of the season, but greatly underperformed in non-conference play and still wasn’t a top SEC team in most outings. I don’t want to quite count him out yet, but the questions are rising for me as to if Mike White can actually get his team to capitalize on their talent and compete for the SEC and have a chance to go deep in March like people continue to expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;georgia-bulldogs&quot;&gt;Georgia Bulldogs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tom Crean is entering his third season in Athens, but this year he doesn’t have a top prospect to build the hype. Anthony Edwards is likely going to be a top five pick in the NBA draft, three other guys gradated, and Rodney Howard is transferring to play for rival Georgia Tech. Rayshaun Hammonds has also declared for the NBA Draft, but it would be odd for him to remain in and not return for his senior season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bulldogs have signed two 4-star high school prospects and two top ten JUCO guys to help replenish the roster for next season. I’m not sure if this will be enough to replace Anthony Edwards, but there are still five other players from last year’s class, including Sahvir Wheeler, who will have a year of experience under their belt and could make a bigger difference in their sophomore campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with Rayshaun Hammonds back, Georgia will still just have him and Tye Fagan as the only Junior and Senior on the roster. Because of this, I think the biggest question remaining for Georgia right now is which player fills the last roster spot. I believe that a graduate transfer with immediate eligibility and the ability to add needed experience would be ideal. I believe Justin Kier would be a fantastic option to fill this last spot, but the George Mason transfer is also considering Arkansas, Georgetown, Iowa State, Michigan, Minnesota, and NC State as finalists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kentucky-wildcats&quot;&gt;Kentucky Wildcats&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In typical Kentucky fashion, the Wildcats are losing five guys to the NBA draft as well as Johnny Juzang and Kahlil Whitney deciding to transfer and Nate Sestina finishing his one year in Lexington. Also in line with the norm at Kentucky, John Calipari already has three 5-stars and three 4-stars signed in the 2020 class and has added Creighton graduate transfer Davion Mintz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talent will likely never be a problem while John Calipari is at Kentucky, and next season certainly isn’t an exception. However, the distribution of talent by position is still a concern for the Wildcats. Kentucky missed out on Matt Haarms when the 7’-3” center opted to play his final season at BYU and both high schooler Greg Brown and transfer Marcus Santos-Silva have decided not to join Kentucky for next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With so many players leaving from last year’s regular season SEC champion squad, Kentucky still has three scholarship spots remaining for them to potentially fill. They only have Keion Brooks and the three 4-star prospects listed as forwards, and could definitely use a true big to anchor the front court next season. Filling that need will be the biggest issue for Kentucky right now. The 2021 class could have some options, but right now it’s not looking great for the Wildcat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to pick against Kentucky in the SEC, but Calipari could struggle even more to figure out how to take a “small ball” lineup and still make them SEC champions and major contenders in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lsu-tigers&quot;&gt;LSU Tigers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LSU certainly loses Skyler Mays to graduation, and with Trendon Watford and Darius Days currently declared for the NBA Draft, the Tigers could be losing three of their best players from last season. They’re currently one scholarship spot over for next season, so while I would expect at least one of those two guys to return, they currently don’t have any spots left for them to return (and one more person could potentially leave).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, LSU once again has a nationally relevant recruiting class with a 5-star, two 4-stars, and three 3-stars committed or signed. On top of that the Tigers have signatures from transfers Shareef O’Neal and Josh LeBlanc while Parker Edwards will be available after sitting last season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think LSU has already added enough talent to be good once again next season, especially with the momentum Will Wade has built in the last two few years, but the biggest decision for the Tigers will probably be the eligibility of Shareef O’Neal and Josh LeBlanc. O’Neal in particular would add another valuable option to the Tigers’ front court if he is able to get a waiver for immediate eligibility or the NCAA somehow changes their transfer eligibility rules in time to take effect for the 2020-2021 season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mississippi-rebels&quot;&gt;Mississippi Rebels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going into his third year, Kermit Davis Jr. loses Breein Tyree to graduation and Franco Miller Jr. and Carlos Curry to transfer. Breein Tyree will be a huge loss for the Rebels but with nine other scholarship players returning currently and four other newcomers joining the squad, the experience could be a benefit going into next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it stands, if you count all of the guys committed and signed, I have Ole Miss as being two scholarship spots over, so things could change going into next year, but as it stands, they’ll have more returners than almost anyone in the conference. Kermit Davis has done enough to prove that he’s a good coach, but he might need more than one or two guys to step up for the Rebels to be a contender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My biggest question for Ole Miss going into next season is who will step up and replace the production of Breein Tyree. Devontae Shuler will be back for his Senior year and Khadim Sky was a major contributor in the paint last season, but right now I don’t see an obvious replacement for Tyree and his impressive scoring ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This probably isn’t a question that will be answered until basketball is played, but who steps up to replace Tyree is my biggest question mark for Ole Miss next season. I trust Kermit Davis to continue to be a good coach and having this much experience returning is probably even more important with the uncertainty of COVID-19, so the Rebels could certainly be a dark horse going into next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mississippi-state-bulldogs&quot;&gt;Mississippi State Bulldogs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transfer portal and other forms of departure have not been kind to the Ben Howland as five players have announced they’re transferring, four guys have graduated, and three players have declared for the NBA Draft with Nick Weatherspoon and Robert Woodard II already announcing they plan to stay in. All in all, Mississippi State is losing at least seven scholarship players with the potential to lose one more if Reggie Perry decides to stay in the draft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To counter this mass exodus, the Bulldogs will have transfer Tolu Smith available after sitting out last season and have signed a 4-star and 3-star prospect. There are six scholarships remaining for next year’s Mississippi State Bulldogs, so limiting this to just one question mark for next season seems like an understatement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Abdul Ado has put his name into the draft, it seems very apparent that he will return and be one of the top guys for the Bulldogs next season. Outside of that, they’re going to need a lot of help either from incoming transfers of high school guys that reclassify from the 2021 class. Ben Howland has started to settle down from the other top coaches in the SEC now entering his sixth year, but this will be a very important next few months for him as he tries to build out a team that can try to at least compete for the top half of the league.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;missouri-tigers&quot;&gt;Missouri Tigers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reed Nikko graduated and Tray Jackson transferring are the only for sure departures, but Cuonzo Martin also has to wait to see what Mitchell Smith, Jeremiah Tilmon, and Xavier Pinson decide to do after declaring for the NBA Draft. It’s likely that all three will return and are just testing the waters, and with Missouri having five scholarship spots to fill including them, I’d say it’s looking like they’ll be back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That leaves Missouri with quite a bit of experience returning next season and still two scholarship spots to fill with newcomers. With just one 3-star player committed, the Tigers aren’t exactly reloading, so adding a couple more weapons via transfer or reclassification could help. Who fills the last two spots will make an impact on Missouri going into next season, but it’s not my main question with the Tigers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I’m more curious about the jump that all the Smiths (Mitchell, Dru, and Mark) will make with another year as well as Tilmon, Pinson, and others returning. Missouri should have one of the most experienced rosters next season, and if Cuonzo Martin can get the best out of each of these guys, Missouri might be able to climb the SEC standings. There were flashes of the Tigers putting it together at times last season, but another year of almost the same squad could be just what they need to really compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;south-carolina-gamecocks&quot;&gt;South Carolina Gamecocks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank Martin loses Micaiah Henry and Malik Kotsar to graduation and Jair Bolden to transfer and just replaces them with two 3-star recruits. Normally, this wouldn’t seem like the best recipe for success, but Frank Martin has done enough to prove that he can get a lot out of anything he’s dealt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AJ Lawson and talented freshman Jermaine Couisnard are both returning, so there are key pieces for Frank Martin to work with. However, as the talent in the rest of the league continues to increase quickly, I’m starting to wonder if Frank Martin can work his magic once again. The Gamecocks currently have zero scholarship spots remaining, so there aren’t many decisions or unknowns left to figure out. That leaves South Carolina as one of the most “complete” teams as of this moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That completeness could be a big benefit as Frank Martin will have even more time to figure out how he is going to make all of these pieces work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tennessee-volunteers&quot;&gt;Tennessee Volunteers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tennessee loses Lamonte Turner and Jordan Bowden to graduation and Jalen Johnson is transferring to ETSU, but other than that, Rick Barnes returns a good bit of talent AND has signed a top recruiting class nationally. Two newly available transfers, two 5-stars, a 4-star, and a 3-star dual sport athlete join the Volunteers on top of the leadership and skills of John Fulkerson and Yves Pons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, with a full roster already, and plenty of talent to add to the key players returning, Tennessee doesn’t leave me with a lot of questions and I’m probably already to declare them as the preseason favorite in the SEC and a national contender. Last season was a down year after two straight seasons at the top of the SEC, but it looks like the Volunteers will be right back on top of the league.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m trying to avoid talking too much about my high expectations for Tennessee right now, but I guess my only question is if they can maintain their expectations and finish at near the top when all is said and done in 2021. Rick Barnes has done a fantastic job so far at Tennessee, but if there is one question remaining, it’s if he can get it done at the end of the year (sounds familiar to his time at Texas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;texas-am-aggies&quot;&gt;Texas A&amp;amp;M Aggies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After year one of the Buzz Williams era at Texas A&amp;amp;M, the Aggies lose three players to graduation and one player is transferring. They have replaced them with a 4-star, two 3-stars, and graduate transfer Kevin Marfo from Quinnipiac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Savion Flagg, Quenton Jackson, and Jay Jay Chandler all returning for their Senior season after being significant contributors last season, Buzz Williams has enough to be dangerous in the SEC in year two. However, with all all that returning talent, the Aggies are looking to just have three guys listed as forwards and with Flagg listed as a guard and forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Auburn and Kentucky, among others, Texas A&amp;amp;M’s biggest question will be how Kevin Marfo, and maybe the remaining scholarship spot, are able to anchor the front court. Size is always an important aspect, but as the SEC reaches the league play, it can be a key differentiator between the teams that actually compete for the top of the league and those that stumble down the stretch due to depth and size issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have high expectations for year two of Buzz Williams, but I don’t think A&amp;amp;M has the talent to stand a chance of competing despite their lack of depth in the front court right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vanderbilt-commodores&quot;&gt;Vanderbilt Commodores&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least (well, they might have been the last two years) is the Vanderbilt Commodores. Vanderbilt is losing two guys to the transfer portal and Aaron Nesmith and Saben Lee have declared for the NBA Draft. Nesmith is staying in the draft, but Lee could return, and his decision will be key. Vanderbilt adds three 3-star prospects and will have two transfers eligible after sitting last season. Senior Clevon Brown was also granted another year of eligibility after missing most of last season due to injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vanderbilt has had pretty poor luck the last few years with their top players getting injured and then failing to win in the SEC. Although finishing at the bottom of the league in consecutive years isn’t great, it has at least given some guys to earn experience that they probably wouldn’t have earned without the injuries and specifically last year, Jerry Stackhouse was able to use his first season to play around with rotations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saben Lee’s decision will be the biggest question mark over the coming weeks as he was the biggest “go-to guy” according to KenPom last season. With Lee back to join Scotty Pippen Jr., Clevon Brown, and others, the Commodores should have enough to dig their way out of the bottom of the conference. While Bryce Drew was probably fired prematurely, Stackhouse did a decent job in year one with all things considered and could capitalize even more next season, especially if Saben Lee removes his name from the NBA Draft and returns to Vanderbilt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some teams certainly have bigger question marks than others at this point, I still think there are plenty of major decisions left to be made and rosters to be finalized for people to be making serious predictions for next season. I’ve probably hinted at my thoughts for next season in this post, but really want to save my full analysis and predictions at least until most of the potential contenders have filled most of the holes in their rosters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last season was a down year for the SEC, but the entire conference should be full of potential next season. Even if none of the empty roster spots were filled on teams like Auburn, Kentucky, and Mississippi State, the SEC is already looking at 5-6 teams that can be in the national conversation and there are other teams that could easily surprise people based on the returning talent and who they have coaching their team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping these next 200 days fly by and that the season starts on time, but in the mean time, these are most of the things I’m looking for to really start setting expectations for next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As always, if you notice something I missed, or just want to share your thoughts, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitter.com/jacobvarner&quot;&gt;reach out on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Varner</name></author><category term="SEC" /><summary type="html">It’s that time of year where almost every college basketball writer is putting out their “way too early pre-season polls and rankings” and there has already been quite a bit of information to inform these decisions. However, with 200 days until the season starts (if it starts on time, fingers crossed) there are still quite a few decisions left to be made and many of them will have a decent impact on SEC basketball for the 2020-2021 season.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Auburn basketball games around the country (and world)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/28/auburn-basketball-games-around-the-country-and-world.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Auburn basketball games around the country (and world)" /><published>2020-02-28T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-02-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/28/auburn-basketball-games-around-the-country-and-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/28/auburn-basketball-games-around-the-country-and-world.html">&lt;p&gt;I just recently finished adding the game locations and other information to my
Auburn basketball spreadsheet, so I decided to pull some data on games by city,
state, and venue. Some of this data is still incomplete, because I have yet to
figure out where some games were played in the early 1900’s and in some cases, I
can’t find whether games were even played on the road or at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will be much lighter on “analysis” compared to some of my others, but
I still found it enjoyable breaking the games down by different criteria. A lot
of the data was expected, but there’s some lesser known things in here as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;auburn-basketball-by-state&quot;&gt;Auburn Basketball by State&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn basketball has played games in 35 of the 50 US States plus Washington,
D.C., Puerto Rico, and Mexico. Auburn has wins in each of those states except
for Alaska (0-3), Colorado (0-2), New Mexico (0-1), Wisconsin (0-1),
Massachusetts (0-1), and Iowa (0-1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn has played more than 100 games in Louisiana (123 games), Florida (130),
Mississippi (139), Tennessee (178), Georgia (229), and Alabama (1,437). Auburn
has a losing record in each of those states except for Alabama where the Tigers
have won 65.81% of their games all time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn is undefeated in Washington, DC (9-0), West Virginia (3-0), and Maryland
(2-0). The Tigers are also 11-1 in Puerto Rico and 5-1 in Utah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the states that Auburn has won at least one game, Auburn has the worst
records in Kentucky (9-64), Arkansas (5-21), and Ohio (2-5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-2-28/Auburn Basketball by State.png&quot; alt=&quot;Full breakdown of Auburn Basketball by state sorted by games played&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Auburn basketball games by state, sorted by total games played&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;auburn-basketball-by-city&quot;&gt;Auburn Basketball by City&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn basketball has played in 131 different cities in 114 different seasons of
basketball going all the way back to the 1905-1906 season. Auburn is undefeated
in 30 of those cities and winless in 33 of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, Auburn has played most of their games in current SEC cities.
Auburn has played 50 or more games in Lexington (53), Knoxville (60), Tuscaloosa
(62), Oxford (66), Starkville (70), Baton Rouge (74), Gainesville (77), Athens
(86), Birmingham (88), Nashville (91), Atlanta (113), and Auburn (1,197).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With at least 10 games played, Auburn has the best records in Sewanee (13-1),
Mobile (10-2), Auburn (823-374), Montgomery (25-13), Birmingham (55-32),
Tallahassee (11-7), and Columbia (11-9).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In cities where Auburn has won at least one game, the Tigers have the worst
records in Lexington (3-50), Knoxville (9-51), Fayetteville (5-21), Tuscaloosa
(12-50), Louisville (3-12), and Houston (2-7).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-2-28/Auburn Basketball by City.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auburn Basketball by City&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Auburn Basketball games by city, sorted by
total games played with at least 10 games&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;auburn-basketball-by-venue&quot;&gt;Auburn Basketball by Venue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn basketball has played in five different home venues: The Gymnasium
(1905-1915), Alumni Gym (1915-1946), The Sports Arena (1946-1968),
Beard-Eaves-Memorial Coliseum (1968-2010), and Auburn Arena (2010-present).
Auburn has played in at least 227 different venues all time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than Auburn’s home arenas, the Tigers have played the most games in
Vanderbilt’s Memorial Gymnasium (56 games), Ole Miss’s Tad Smith Coliseum (48),
LSU’s Pete Maravich Assembly Center (46), Stegeman Coliseum (45), Humphrey
Coliseum (43), Garrett Coliseum in Montgomery (33), Kentucky’s Rupp Arena (33),
and Alabama’s Coleman Coliseum (32).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn basketball is undefeated in 54 different venues and winless in 68
different venues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In non-home venues where Auburn has played at least 10 games, they have the best
record in Sewanee’s Juhan Gymnasium (13-1), Bill Burch Gymnasium in Birmingham
(11-2), Boutwell Auditorium in Birmingham (13-5), BJCC in Birmingham (19-10),
Alexander Memorial Coliseum in Atlanta (13-7), Garrett Coliseum in Montgomery
(20-13), and South Carolina’s Colonial Life Arena (6-4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In venues where Auburn has at least one win, they have the worst records at the
Atlanta Athletic Club (1-12), Kentucky’s Rupp Arena (3-30), Georgia Tech’s
Heisman Gymnasium (2-15), Alabama’s Foster Auditorium (1-7), Tennessee’s Stokely
Center (3-19), and Tennessee’s Thompson-Boling Arena (3-18).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn basketball’s best home venues by record are The Sports Arena (165-54,
75.34%), Auburn Arena (115-53, 68.45%), Beard-Eaves-Memorial Coliseum (392-181,
68.41%), The Gymnasium (27-13, 67.50%), and Alumni Gym (124-73, 62.94%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-2-28/Auburn Basketball by Venue.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auburn Basketball by Venue&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Auburn Basketball games by venue, sorted
by total games played with at least 15 games&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there is a lot more data than can easily be covered in this post, I’ve
added the complete data from each of these breakdowns to a separate spreadsheet
that you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1eT3nzAnK3zFnL45LLWfgxvBAmq368-a-Yd7VyWhKR8o/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;view here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this information took awhile to gather and enter, so I thought it would
be worth using for a post. I hope to be back to more “analysis” in future posts,
but if you enjoy just looking at breakdowns for stuff like this, let me know. I
still have to go and enter opposing coaches for every team and can probably find
some cool trends from that as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, thanks for reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War Eagle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Varner</name></author><category term="Auburn" /><category term="History" /><summary type="html">I just recently finished adding the game locations and other information to my Auburn basketball spreadsheet, so I decided to pull some data on games by city, state, and venue. Some of this data is still incomplete, because I have yet to figure out where some games were played in the early 1900’s and in some cases, I can’t find whether games were even played on the road or at home.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An overview of KenPom, the NET, and other official metrics used by the NCAA Tournament selection committee in 2020</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/21/an-overview-of-kenpom-net-and-other-official-metrics-used-by-the-ncaa-tournament-selection-committee-in-2020.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An overview of KenPom, the NET, and other official metrics used by the NCAA Tournament selection committee in 2020" /><published>2020-02-21T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-02-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/21/an-overview-of-kenpom-net-and-other-official-metrics-used-by-the-ncaa-tournament-selection-committee-in-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/21/an-overview-of-kenpom-net-and-other-official-metrics-used-by-the-ncaa-tournament-selection-committee-in-2020.html">&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, the NCAA officially ditched the RPI (finally) and introduced a
new metric, the NET, that is supposed to encompass more modern ways of
evaluating team performance. Along with the NET, the NCAA also uses five other
official metrics when the selection committee is deciding which teams make the
NCAA Tournament and what seed they will receive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between the change to the NET being new and the many misconceptions of other
advanced metrics and rating systems like KenPom that I see on my Twitter
timeline quite often this time of year, I thought I would try to do my best to
explain the different metrics and how the NCAA uses them to pick the 68 teams
that take part in the best sporting event of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCAA has
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncaa.org/about/resources/media-center/mens-basketball-selections-101-selections&quot;&gt;a nice page explaining their new selection criteria&lt;/a&gt;
if you want to double check the things I cover, but I am going to try to go into
more detail and also explain the other five metrics that they officially use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, there is still a group of people deciding which teams
make the NCAA Tournament and what seed they receive. One of the more common
misconceptions I see where people believe that the NET rankings directly
indicate what seed a team will receive, which isn’t the case at all. There are
no rankings that seed the tournament on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The selection committee officially uses the NET, ESPN’s Strength of Record and
BPI, KPI, KenPom, and the Sagarin rankings to evaluate each team. The NET is
also used with a new quadrant system that categorizes wins and losses as Quad 1,
2, 3 or 4 games based on the ranking of the opponent and where the game is
played.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The committee has also said they they do take player’s missing games into
consideration as long as the player is back for the NCAA Tournament. I have not
seen any specifics on how exactly they take this into consideration, but it’s
safe to say a team that loses a few games while a top player is out is seen as
more favorable than a team with a similar resume or slightly resume that didn’t
lose any key players to injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the NET, which is a combination of both, the five other metrics that
the NCAA uses are broken into two groups: results based metrics and predictive
metrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, here is an overview of the six metrics included on each team’s official
team sheet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-ncaa-evaluation-tool-net&quot;&gt;The NCAA Evaluation Tool (NET)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned above, the NET is the new official metric of the NCAA and is
basically an improved replacement for the RPI. The NET is supposed to be a more
modern metric that includes “the Team Value index, which is based on game
results and factors game location, the opponent and outcome, as well as net
efficiency, winning percentage, adjusted winning percentage, and a capped
scoring margin.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official formula has not been released for the NET, but the rankings are
updated daily for most of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NET is what is used to determine what quadrant each game is and rankings are
taken at the end of the year for Selection Sunday. For instance, a team may get
a win that counts as a Quad 1 win at the time, but if that other team finished
the year poorly, it may slide to a Quad 2 win by the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the NET says that it caps the impact of margin of victory, some still
criticize it because the efficiency component is most likely still not capped.
This is still technically speculation because seemingly no one knows the
official algorithm used to generate the rankings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;espn-strength-of-record&quot;&gt;ESPN Strength of Record&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strength of Record is one of the two results based metrics that the NCAA uses
and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.espn.com/mens-college-basketball/bpi/_/dir/asc/view/overview/sort/sorrank&quot;&gt;ESPN describes it as&lt;/a&gt;
“a measure of team accomplishment based on how difficult a team’s W-L record is
to achieve.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strength of Record is similar to a strength of schedule metric, but it actually
matters if a team wins the tough games instead of just playing them. For
instance, Kansas has the 7th best strength of schedule according to ESPN, but
their 23-3 record gives them the 2nd ranked Strength of Record while Baylor has
the best Strength of Record currently by having a 24-1 record against the 33rd
toughest schedule (and a road win over Kansas) as of 2/20/2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, Minnesota has the toughest strength of schedule, but still is ranked
60th in Strength of Record because they’ve gone 12-13 against that schedule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kevin-pauga-index-kpi&quot;&gt;Kevin Pauga Index (KPI)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://faktor.ddns.net/#/&quot;&gt;KPI&lt;/a&gt; is a results based metric developed by now
Assistant Director of Athletics at Michigan State,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kpisports.net/about/&quot;&gt;Kevin Pauga&lt;/a&gt;. The KPI started as a large
Excel sheet and has developed into a comprehensive metric used by college
basketball and other sports over the last decade plus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The KPI assigns a value for each game based on the opponent and location and
then uses the aggregate of each games score to rank teams. For instance,
Auburn’s best win of the season was 0.77 at Mississippi State while their worst
loss was -0.11 at Missouri. Auburn currently sits in 5th overall with a rating
of 0.367, just 0.001 ahead of both Villanova and Creighton at 0.366 as of
2/20/2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each team also has a rating for strength of schedule, overall differential,
offensive differential, and defensive differential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because each game is assigned a score, it’s easy to see the best wins and losses
of the season. Baylor has the best win of the season so far with a 1.13 at
Kansas while Grand Canyon and Hampton have the worst losses of the season with
-1.01 results against a non-D1 opponent and Howard, both at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ken-pomeroy-ratings-kenpom&quot;&gt;Ken Pomeroy Ratings (KenPom)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KenPom has been the metric I reference the most on Twitter, mostly because the
site also provides a ton of other good information for each team. The
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kenpom.com&quot;&gt;KenPom rankings&lt;/a&gt; are one of the predictive metrics used
and they are
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kenpomeroy/status/1229504597716160512&quot;&gt;“not trying to measure accomplishment.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the most basic sense, KenPom ranks teams based on the difference between
their adjusted offensive efficiency and adjusted defensive efficiency. KenPom
does not disclose his exact formula, but it adjusts each teams efficiency (how
many points they score or give up per 100 possessions) to account for the level
of competition they have played.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that how efficient a team is is more important than results and hence
why the rankings are supposed to be an indication of how a team will perform in
the future and not an assessment of their resume. Yes, winning helps because a
win means that a team has a higher offensive efficiency than defensive
efficiency for the game, but wins (even over good teams) don’t always lead to
big jumps in the rankings, especially later in the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KenPom also allows for pretty easy comparison between teams from year to year.
For instance, Kansas is the best KenPom team with an adjusted net efficiency of
+30.99 as of me writing this. However, they would only be the 3rd best team last
year with that efficiency. In fact, the top 8 teams at the end of last season
are “better” than the second best team this season (Baylor, +27.54).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many of the other advanced metrics, KenPom also has a calculation for
different strengths of schedule as well as things like “luck” which are
seemingly factored into the adjustment to the efficiencies that are then used
for the final ratings and rankings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;espn-basketball-power-index-bpi&quot;&gt;ESPN Basketball Power Index (BPI)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The BPI is ESPN’s predictive metric that they describe as
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.espn.com/mens-college-basketball/bpi&quot;&gt;“a measure of team strength that is meant to be the best predictor of performance going forward.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not been able to find a detailed description of how the BPI is calculated
or what it’s mostly based on, but it is at least broken down into an two metrics
for offense and defense that are added together to get the actual BPI rating
which is used to rank teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, Duke is the overall BPI leader at 18.4 while Gonzaga has the best
offense (12.9) and West Virginia has the best defense (10.3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sagarin-ratings&quot;&gt;Sagarin Ratings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff Sagarin’s ratings, like KPI, are used for many other sports and therefore
are not just basketball specific. The ratings also only factor in games against
D1 opponents. Sagarin’s ratings are a predictive metric, and he even says that
to predict the outcome of a given game, just compare the two team’s ratings and
then simply add an adjustment to the home team (the exact amount for adjustment
changes as the season goes based on more data gathered).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not reference Sagarin as often and am not as familiar with the ratings, but
you can get a pretty good explanation
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usatoday.com/sports/ncaab/sagarin/&quot;&gt;directly on the site&lt;/a&gt;. Like
others, Sagarin has his own rating for schedule which ranks teams based on
strength of schedule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sagarin has three ratings that are combined to create the overall rating for
each team: a predictor rating based on expected future scores, a golden mean
rating that utilizes actual scores from games played, and a recent rating which
puts more emphasis on recent games in order to account for upward and downward
trends for a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, Auburn is currently 44th overall, with a predictor ranking of 28,
a golden mean ranking of 22, and a recent ranking of 78 which brings the overall
down quite a bit following two straight double digit losses to bad teams as of
writing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, computer rankings are a major asset for the NCAA
Tournament selection committee because college basketball in particular has a
large number of teams competing against each other and with just 30ish regular
season games to consider, schedules are certainly not going to overlap much.
Computer rankings and metrics allow for teams to be normalized and easily
compared based on many different factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCAA selection committee uses six different metrics (and two different types
of metrics) because each one looks at different things and the rankings can be
quite different across the board. If the committee only went of KPI for example,
Auburn would be the top 2 seed and has been a 1 seed for most of recent weeks.
However, based on Sagarin, Auburn would barely be an 11 seed in the tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The committee looks at each of these metrics to get a sense of how good a team
is but then still look ats head to head results, “the eye test”, and other
things as I mentioned at the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing definitely not factored into this is human opinion polls like the AP
and Coaches poll. Those polls are great for teams to market and TV networks to
put numbers by team names, but at the end of the season, they are pretty much
meaningless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve linked to different explanations and ranking throughout the article, but to
make it easy, here is where you can find each official ranking if you want to
check throughout the rest of the season to see how your team is doing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncaa.com/rankings/basketball-men/d1/ncaa-mens-basketball-net-rankings&quot;&gt;NET&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.espn.com/mens-college-basketball/bpi&quot;&gt;ESPN SoR and BPI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://faktor.ddns.net/#/&quot;&gt;KPI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kenpom.com&quot;&gt;KenPom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usatoday.com/sports/ncaab/sagarin/&quot;&gt;Sagarin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that this post did a good enough job of explaining each of the metrics
used by the NCAA selection committee and breaking down the components that go
into each rating and how they should be interpreted. At the end of the day, it
is still humans picking teams and seeding the NCAA tournament, so there will be
things that cannot always be explained, but hopefully this post makes it easier
to understand what factors went into your team getting a certain seed or missing
the tournament altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, if you have any additional questions, or think something is explained
wrong in this post, please feel free to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitter.com&quot;&gt;let me know on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Varner</name></author><category term="General" /><summary type="html">A few years ago, the NCAA officially ditched the RPI (finally) and introduced a new metric, the NET, that is supposed to encompass more modern ways of evaluating team performance. Along with the NET, the NCAA also uses five other official metrics when the selection committee is deciding which teams make the NCAA Tournament and what seed they will receive.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Calculating relative game performance and statistically awarding MVPs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/14/calculating-relative-game-performance-and-statistically-awarding-mvps.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Calculating relative game performance and statistically awarding MVPs" /><published>2020-02-14T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-02-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/14/calculating-relative-game-performance-and-statistically-awarding-mvps</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/14/calculating-relative-game-performance-and-statistically-awarding-mvps.html">&lt;p&gt;In this post, I explain how I use stats and different metrics to determine
relative game performance and then award a most valuable player for each games
as well as rank the overall contribution for each player in each game. As I
explain throughout the post, each of these metrics offer a fun way to evaluate
players in the context of singe games, single seasons, or entire careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-idea&quot;&gt;The Idea&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the idea of awarding a “Game MVP” statistically from
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kenpom.com/&quot;&gt;Ken Pomeroy&lt;/a&gt;. However, unlike Pomeroy’s site, I award
an MVP for every Auburn game, whether they win or lose. I don’t believe that
Pomeroy indicates what combination of statistics he uses to decide which player
is the MVP, but after using my own criteria, I came to the same conclusion on
Auburn’s MVP for almost all of their wins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to have an MVP metric for Auburn so that I could keep track of players
that have occasion big games, are consistently an important factor, or are
either really good or really bad. While my stat is officially used to calculate
the MVP of each game, it also goes ahead and ranks the performances of every
player that sees the court in a game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what allows me to calculate an “average MVP placement” for each game as
well as track how many games a player finishes in the top 3 or top 5 of a game
indicating that they were a major factor on the game or at least deserved to be
a starter in that game (I realize that there are many things that factor into
determining starters and that some players contribute more off the bench for
various reasons).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-calculation&quot;&gt;My Calculation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My method is rather simple, while the calculation is not. In order to award an
MVP and assign relative performance rankings for each game, I just use the
offensive contribution percentage for each player in the game. This metric is
just each players Adjusted Game Score relative to the other players in the game
on the same team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game Score is credited to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://theathletic.com/author/john-hollinger/&quot;&gt;John Hollinger&lt;/a&gt; and is a box
score based metric that takes into account most individual stats in order to
give a good measure of player productivity for the game. Adjusted Game Score
just normalizes each player’s Game Score to reflect the actual points the team
scored. The calculations I use are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;GameScore = Pts + 0.4*FGM - 0.7*FGA - 0.4*(FTA - FTM) \\ + 0.7*OREB + 0.3*DREB + STL \\ + 0.7*AST + 0.7*BLK - 0.4*PF - TOV&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;AdjGameScore = \frac{GameScore}{TeamGameScore} * TeamPts&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offensive Percentage is then just each Individual Adjusted Game Score as a
percentage of the Team Game Score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;auburn-basketball-mvps-from-2010-2020&quot;&gt;Auburn Basketball MVPs from 2010-2020&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I like the Offensive Percentage stat is because it can easily be
extended to a full season to show who had the most contribution across all key
stats throughout the year. While there can be other factors when voting on a
player with the “eye test” or combining more stats that people find valuable,
these are the MVPs for Auburn basketball over the last decade:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-2-14/Auburn Basketball Season MVPs for 2010-2020.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auburn Basketball Season MVPs for 2010-2020&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Auburn Basketball Season
MVPs for 2010-2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things immediately stuck out to me when looking at the MVPs for the past
ten seasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, KT Harrell,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://hoops.jacobvarner.com/breaking-down-individual-win-loss-records-for-auburn-basketball-in-the-bruce-pearl-era/&quot;&gt;as discussed in my post earlier&lt;/a&gt;
was a major part in willing the 2014-2015 team to wins, even if they were
infrequent. This immediately highlights that Offensive Percentage, like some
other stats, can be greatly affected by the quality of other players on the
team. The next best player on the 2014-2015 team was Cinmeon Bowers at 16.78%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, Jared Harper was awesome (I can’t state this enough) and was obviously
important to Auburn. Harper benefits here because he was a player that could do
a little bit of everything, and that’s pretty much what is supposed to be
reflected in Adjusted Game Score and Offensive Percentage. Along with doing lots
of things well, Harper benefits from being one of the more consistent players,
which I’ll touch on later when looking at game MVPs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the seasons were really close, like in 2011-2012 where Frankie Sullivan
had an Offensive Percentage of 20.22% and only trailed Kenny Gabriel by 0.44%
for the season MVP. Chuma Okeke was also less than a percent away from Jared
Harper’s MVP season in 2018-2019 and the last two games could have made a
difference since Offensive Percentage does not account for missed games when
looking at a full season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;most-mvps-in-a-season-from-2010-2020&quot;&gt;Most MVPs in a Season from 2010-2020&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Offensive Percentage certainly does a better job of showing consistency
throughout the season, it’s also worthwhile to take a look at total number of
games where a player was the best player in that individual game. Below are the
ten highest MVPs in a season for players in the 2010-2020 seasons (no 2019-2020
players make the list because there have only been 24 games played at the time
of writing this), as well as the number of games played and number of starts,
which give more perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-2-14/Top Ten Game MVPs in a Season for 2010-2020.png&quot; alt=&quot;Top Ten Game MVPs in a Season for 2010-2020&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Top Ten Game MVPs in a
Season for 2010-2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that immediately stood out to me in this list was Chris Denson
being the best player for Auburn 10 times in 2012-2013 despite only playing 20
games and starting 9 of them. In fact, half of his MVP games, he came off of the
bench. In the final three games of the season (all off the bench, and all game
MVPs), Chris Denson posted Offensive Percentages of 40.26%, 40.17%, and 26.78%!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cinmeon Bowers was a pretty good second option for the 2014-2015 team as he
brought in 11 game MVPs, good for 5th in the past decade, despite being 13th in
season Offensive Percentage in the same time period. At first I thought this
stat was even weirder, but
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jacobvarner/status/1228167920812838914?s=20&quot;&gt;then realized that my Game Score stat that these are based off of was totally broken&lt;/a&gt;
in a game where Bowers scored 17 points and pulled down 15 rebounds but Auburn
still lost to Tulsa 35-53 and posted a team Game Score of -1.1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You didn’t need a chart to tell you this, but Jared Harper, Bryce Brown, and
Chuma Okeke were quite the three headed attack in 2018-2019 with the three of
them combining for 31 of the teams game MVPs and all three individually
finishing in the top 10 for the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;total-game-mvps-top-3s-and-top-5s&quot;&gt;Total Game MVPs, Top 3s, and Top 5s&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way I like to get a good overall picture to to look at the players that
not only have the most MVPs, but also compare the number of times that they
finish the game in the Top 3 or Top 5. In addition, the average placement, which
has a best case scenario of 1 (if the player was the MVP in every game they
played in) and a worst case scenario equal to the number of players on the
roster that year. Here are the results for the players with double digit game
MVPs in the last decade:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-2-14/Most Individual Game MVPs from 2010-2020.png&quot; alt=&quot;Most Individual Game MVPs from 2010-2020&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Most Individual Game MVPs
from 2010-2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The table favors KT Harrell once again as the transfer guard gathered 24 game
MVPs in just 64 games across his two seasons playing for Auburn. Harrell also
finished just 3 of his 64 games outside of the top 5 players in a game, which is
why he started all 64 games while he was at Auburn under both Tony Barbee and
Bruce Pearl. Harrell also has the best average MVP placement for his career at
2.36.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jared Harper posted 25 game MVPs, 55 games in the top 3, and 81 games in the top
5 which was good enough for second on this list. This is even more impressive
considering Harper did this in just three years at Auburn and had the potential
to most likely easily overtake Chris Denson if Harper had stayed for a senior
season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know that Bryce Brown had the ability to get hot, and that seemed to
happen more frequently than not in his last two seasons at Auburn, but this stat
shows that Brown also had his fair share of cold games with one of the lower
average MVP placements on this list at 4.69. Brown still had the most games
played in the decade and second most games where he finished in the top 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this post, I have just finished adding team and individual game stats
going back to the 2010-11 season, which means I now have stats for every Tony
Barbee and Bruce Pearl coached team. Stats and metrics like this were
interesting to look at for the past decade, because they’re determined by player
skill as well as the overall talent on a team, which means players for both Tony
Barbee and Bruce Pearl have the ability to show their relative worth to each of
the teams they were on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this was another interesting metric and my explanations made sense. As
always, if you have questions or want to see more of this data for other groups
of players, just &lt;a href=&quot;https://wwww.twitter.com/jacobvarner&quot;&gt;let me know on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading and War Eagle!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Varner</name></author><category term="Auburn" /><category term="Stats" /><summary type="html">In this post, I explain how I use stats and different metrics to determine relative game performance and then award a most valuable player for each games as well as rank the overall contribution for each player in each game. As I explain throughout the post, each of these metrics offer a fun way to evaluate players in the context of singe games, single seasons, or entire careers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Auburn basketball offensive and defensive efficiencies in the Bruce Pearl era - with graphs!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/07/auburn-basketball-offensive-and-defensive-efficiencies-in-the-bruce-pearl-era-with-graphs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Auburn basketball offensive and defensive efficiencies in the Bruce Pearl era - with graphs!" /><published>2020-02-07T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-02-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/07/auburn-basketball-offensive-and-defensive-efficiencies-in-the-bruce-pearl-era-with-graphs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/07/auburn-basketball-offensive-and-defensive-efficiencies-in-the-bruce-pearl-era-with-graphs.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most essential “advanced metrics” that I (and a lot of people) use to
judge teams is offensive and defensive efficiency. It’s a common metric for
comparing NBA teams and is also useful in college basketball, although, as with
a lot of things, the majorly unbalanced schedules in college cause there to be
some caveats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have near the amount of data as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kenpomery.com&quot;&gt;Ken Pomeroy&lt;/a&gt;
or other bigger sites, so my offensive and defensive efficiencies (also called
ratings) don’t factor in opponents, so they’re NOT adjusted efficiencies. This
is not as big a deal when just looking at one team, but I’ll try to note when
games are against either very good or very bad teams in order to put some of the
more impressive wins into perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;explaining-efficiencies-and-possessions&quot;&gt;Explaining Efficiencies and Possessions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I get too far into this, I want to give a basic explanation of offensive
and defensive efficiency. In the most basic sense, each efficiency is just the
number of points that the Auburn (for offensive efficiency) or their opponent
(for defensive efficiency) scored if the game had had 100 possessions. This
normalizes the ratings for teams or games that are faster or slower tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, a team that scores 90 points but has 80 possessions in a game
isn’t as impressive as a team that scores 80 points with just 65 possessions in
a game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan on doing another post in the future going into the details of how I
calculate possessions and other common metrics in my spreadsheet, but for now,
possessions are just calculated using shots, rebounds, and turnovers for both
teams, and then averaged out. This isn’t always exactly accurate because it’s
just based on the box score, but it allows me to calculate possessions for games
all the time even if actual possessions were not tracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overview-of-my-graphs-used-in-this-post&quot;&gt;Overview of my Graphs Used in this Post&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the graphs I use in this post all show the offensive efficiency,
defensive efficiency, and net efficiency (offense minus defense) for each game
of the season. I’ve also plotted a line that is a running average of the
offensive and defensive efficiencies as the season progresses. With this, a game
with a higher offensive efficiency than defensive efficiency is a win for Auburn
and any games for both metrics above the average are “good” games at that point
in the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The offensive efficiencies are in green while the defensive efficiencies are in
red. The yellow line at the bottom is the net efficiency which shows whether
Auburn won or loss if it is positive or negative, as well as the margin of
victory or margin of defeat in a tempo free way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Since this is my first time using graphs with my stats, I’m definitely open to
feedback on things that can be better conveyed. Feel free to let me know
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitter.com/jacobvarner&quot;&gt;on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2019-2020-season&quot;&gt;2019-2020 Season&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Record:&lt;/strong&gt; 20-2 (through 22 games)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Average Opponent KenPom Ranking:&lt;/strong&gt; 98.18&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 25 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 50 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 100 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-2-7/Auburn Basketball Efficiency for the 2019-2020 Season.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auburn Basketball Efficiency for the 2019-2020 Season&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve mentioned several times on Twitter that the Alabama and Florida games this
season were major outliers. In fact, they were two of the worst offensive games
Auburn has played individually in the Bruce Pearl era and were the worst
back-to-back games during his tenure. As a result, the net efficiency also takes
a big dip in those games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another game of note is the win over Cal State Northridge where Auburn had the
second best offensive efficiency in the Bruce Pearl era with 141.7 points per
100 possessions as well as the fifth best net efficiency at 56.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is the first season since 2015-2016 that the offensive efficiency for
the season hasn’t improved on the previous year, the current season average for
defensive efficiency is the best in the Bruce Pearl era by almost 5 points at
95.9 points per 100 possessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, Auburn doesn’t have the best strength of schedule based on average
KenPom ranking for opponents, but that should improve as Auburn continues to
face above average teams in conference play and hopefully has a longer post
season similar to last season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2018-2019-season&quot;&gt;2018-2019 Season&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Record:&lt;/strong&gt; 30-10&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Average Opponent KenPom Ranking:&lt;/strong&gt; 69.44&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 25 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 50 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 100 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-2-7/Auburn Basketball Efficiency for the 2018-2019 Season.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auburn Basketball Efficiency for the 2018-2019 Season&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2018-2019 season was much more up or down, especially at the beginning of
the season, and that can be seen by the very jagged lines for both offensive and
defensive efficiency. However, the team clearly got hot at the perfect time
three games with over a 20 net efficiency in the SEC and NCAA Tournaments
against Tennessee, Kansas, and North Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the opponents certainly weren’t the toughest challenges, Auburn posted
their two best defensive performances back to back against Saint Peter’s and UNC
Asheville with defensive efficiencies of 64.5 and 62.0 respectively. The Saint
Peter’s game was the best net efficiency performance in the Bruce Pearl era
(albeit against a team ranked 235th in KenPom at the time) and the UNC Asheville
game was the best defensive efficiency performance in the Bruce Pearl era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 140.7 offensive efficiency in the first game of the season against South
Alabama is the second best offensive performance in the Bruce Pearl era (against
a team ranked 174 in KenPom at the time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the 2018-2019 team posted the best offensive efficiency for a season in
the Bruce Pearl era and the best defensive efficiency for a season up until this
season. All of this was against the best overall set of opponents that Auburn
has faced under Bruce Pearl thanks to an invite the Maui Invitational and then a
run all the way through the SEC Tournament followed by a Final Four appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2017-2018-season&quot;&gt;2017-2018 Season&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Record:&lt;/strong&gt; 26-8&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Average Opponent KenPom Ranking:&lt;/strong&gt; 94.41&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 25 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 50 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 100 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-2-7/Auburn Basketball Efficiency for the 2017-2018 Season.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auburn Basketball Efficiency for the 2017-2018 Season&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2017-2018 team was off to a similar start to the 2019-2020 team but then you
can clearly see where Anfernee McLemore went down with a season ending injury in
the 27th game against South Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn’s best offensive game of the season came in game five against Winthrop
where Auburn scored 145.3 points per 100 possessions. That game is also the best
offensive game in the Bruce Pearl era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn posted its two best defensive performances in the second game of the
season against Indiana State (79.5 points per 100 possessions), and the second
to last game of the season against College of Charleston (79.1 points per 100
possessions). The College of Charleston game came at a perfect time which saved
Auburn’s poor offense of just 84.6 points per 100 possessions and allowed Auburn
to remain undefeated in opening round NCAA Tournament games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2016-2017-season&quot;&gt;2016-2017 Season&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Record:&lt;/strong&gt; 18-14&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Average Opponent KenPom Ranking:&lt;/strong&gt; 105.09&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 25 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 50 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 100 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-2-7/Auburn Basketball Efficiency for the 2016-2017 Season.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auburn Basketball Efficiency for the 2016-2017 Season&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2016-2017 season was the first winning season under Bruce Pearl and the
first winning season for Auburn since the 2008-2009 season under Jeff Lebo.
Auburn may have had a winning record, but it was against Bruce Pearl’s worst set
of opponents based on KenPom average ranking and was up and down almost the
entire way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn’s biggest win of the year came against Coastal Carolina and former coach
Cliff Ellis where Auburn posted a 137.0 offensive efficiency, 84.3 defensive
efficiency, and 52.7 net efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Florida game at home in the 26th game of the season was the second worst
defensive performance of the Bruce Pearl era where Auburn gave up a miserable
140.7 points per 100 possessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2015-2016-season&quot;&gt;2015-2016 Season&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Record:&lt;/strong&gt; 11-20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Average Opponent KenPom Ranking:&lt;/strong&gt; 88.97&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 25 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 50 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 100 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-2-7/Auburn Basketball Efficiency for the 2015-2016 Season.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auburn Basketball Efficiency for the 2015-2016 Season&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015-2016, Auburn had probably the hardest regular season in the Bruce Pearl
era with an average KenPom ranking of opponents of 88.97 without playing more
than one postseason game. While the schedule didn’t present a lot of easy games,
Auburn still finished with the worst record under Bruce Pearl and worst season
record since Tony Barbee’s team in 2012-2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a lot of bad performances on both ends of the court, Auburn still posted
the third best offensive performance under Bruce Pearl with 140.6 points per 100
possession against Northwestern State in the fourth game of the season. The game
was the best offensive performance of the year and was 25.2 points per 100
possessions better than every other game the rest of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very last game of the season was the worst defensively where Auburn gave up
141.0 points per 100 possessions against Tennessee in the first round of the SEC
Tournament. The game was also the worst defensive performance by Auburn in the
Bruce Pearl era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2014-2015-season&quot;&gt;2014-2015 Season&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Record:&lt;/strong&gt; 15-20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Average Opponent KenPom Ranking:&lt;/strong&gt; 88.79&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 25 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 50 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 100 KenPom Opponents:&lt;/strong&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-2-7/Auburn Basketball Efficiency for the 2014-2015 Season.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auburn Basketball Efficiency for the 2014-2015 Season&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at the averages for offensive and defensive efficiency as the year
went on, it’s pretty clear the the 2014-2015 was pretty even on both ends of the
court but couldn’t put both sides together very often (until the end of the
year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right before the end of the regular season, Auburn posted four straight games
with offensive efficiencies below 100. It looked like it was going to be a rough
ending for Bruce Pearl’s first season at Auburn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Tigers actually turned up the defense in the SEC Tournament with
three games at 95.2, 84.0, and 95.0 points allowed per 100 possessions on the
way to wins over Mississippi State, Texas A&amp;amp;M, and LSU. Those would be the first
wins in the SEC Tournament for Auburn since the 2008-2009 season under Jeff
Lebo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn ran out of gas and met the then undefeated Kentucky Wildcats and their
net efficiency took a nose dive to end the season in the SEC Tournament Semifinal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I think offensive and defensive efficiency are two of the best stats for
judging teams on a level playing field without overhyping defenses that play
slow or offenses that play fast. I hope the metrics make sense and help paint an
overall picture for both sides of the ball under Bruce Pearl at Auburn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, if you have any questions about specific data points or explanations
in this post, please don’t hesitate to reach out to me
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitter.com/jacobvarner&quot;&gt;on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks for taking the time to
read my overview of Auburn basketball offensive and defensive efficiencies under
Bruce Pearl and I hope the graphs made it more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War Eagle!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Varner</name></author><category term="Auburn" /><category term="Stats" /><summary type="html">One of the most essential “advanced metrics” that I (and a lot of people) use to judge teams is offensive and defensive efficiency. It’s a common metric for comparing NBA teams and is also useful in college basketball, although, as with a lot of things, the majorly unbalanced schedules in college cause there to be some caveats.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking down individual win-loss records for Auburn basketball in the Bruce Pearl era</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/31/breaking-down-individual-win-loss-records-for-auburn-basketball-in-the-bruce-pearl-era.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking down individual win-loss records for Auburn basketball in the Bruce Pearl era" /><published>2020-01-31T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-01-31T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/31/breaking-down-individual-win-loss-records-for-auburn-basketball-in-the-bruce-pearl-era</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/31/breaking-down-individual-win-loss-records-for-auburn-basketball-in-the-bruce-pearl-era.html">&lt;p&gt;So the idea/reason for this post goes back to a few tweets I had earlier this
month about the individual win-loss records for Auburn basketball players so far
this season:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;tweet-wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Assuming I have the calculation right, I&amp;#39;m getting the following individual W-L for this year&amp;#39;s Auburn major contributers so far:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Doughty: 1.82 - 0.91&lt;br /&gt;Okoro: 2.09 - 0.39&lt;br /&gt;McCormick: 1.66 - 0.87&lt;br /&gt;Purifoy: 1.59 - 0.43&lt;br /&gt;Wiley: 2.07 - 0.14&lt;br /&gt;McLemore: 1.49 - 0.15&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jacob Varner 👨‍💻 🏀 🌮 (@jacobvarner) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jacobvarner/status/1219104474414960640?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 20, 2020&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to explain the calculations the in a general since on Twitter, but it’s
obviously hard in even a series of tweets, so I’m going to attempt to explain it
and some other related stats here while also diving more into this data for the
entire Bruce Pearl era and looking at some interesting standouts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;individual-win-loss-records-explained&quot;&gt;Individual Win-Loss Records Explained&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the concept of individual win-loss records from advanced analytics pioneer
Dean Oliver, and specifically his book “Basketball on Paper.” Oliver is mostly
associated with the NBA, and so some things don’t directly translate to college,
especially in the context of one team, in my case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, in my most basic explanation, individual win-loss records are supposed
to show how much each individual player contributed to the wins and losses of
the season. The best players should contribute more wins and less losses. While
not practical, I like to think of this stat as showing what a teams record would
be if you just had five of that one player playing all season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oliver’s stat takes into account two main things: the individual winning
percentage for a player and the individual contributions to games the player
has. Individual winning percentage is fairly easy to calculate, assuming you
already have the individual offensive and defensive ratings for the player
(those are fairly complicated, but you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.basketball-reference.com/about/ratings.html&quot;&gt;read about them here&lt;/a&gt;
or in Oliver’s book I just mentioned).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest version of individual win percentage, which Oliver credits to Bill
James, is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;IndWin\% = \frac{ORtg^2}{ORtg^2 + DRtg^2}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “games responsible for” stat is a little more complex, and I had to make
some slight modifications to make it fit to Auburn and the data that I have
available to me. Oliver uses four different metrics, percentage of team
offensive possessions contributed to, percentage of team defensive stops made,
percentage of team minutes played, and percentage of team games started. Oliver
gives more weight to the first two for reasons he explains in his book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was getting these to work for Auburn, I found that the percentage of
games started skewed the data too much since Auburn plays a 30–40 game schedule
versus the NBA 82 game minimum. I also figured this portion was accounted for
enough with the percentage of minutes played.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for my final adaption of the formula, I calculated games contributed to as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;GmResp = \frac{3*OffPoss\% + 3*DefStop\% + Min\%}{7} * TotalGames&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the percentage of offensive possessions and percentage of team defensive
stops are factored into ORtg and DRtg, so their explanation is covered in the
link above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the individual win-loss record is simply calculated as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;IndWins = GmResp * IndWin\%&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;IndLosses = GmResp * (1 - IndWin\%)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m by no means an expert, and have never been a teacher, so that’s the best I
think I can do in explaining the stat to others. As with almost any of my stats
I use or reference, feel free to leave a comment below or
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitter.com/jacobvarner&quot;&gt;reply on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and I’ll do my best to
explain it further if I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;individual-win-loss-records-for-auburn-players&quot;&gt;Individual Win-Loss Records for Auburn Players&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a sense of what the stat looks like with actual data behind it, here are
the individual results for the past two seasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-1-31/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Individual Win-Loss Records for Auburn basketball's major contributors so far in the 2019-2020 season&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;2019-2020 Season (Through 20 games)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-1-31/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Individual Win-Loss Records for Auburn basketball's major contributors in the 2018-2020 season&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;2018-2019 Season (40 games)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve sorted each of these tables by the games responsible for, the it should be
in order of the most impactful player, whether they contribute in a good way or
bad way, they’re making the most contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the 2019–2020 season, the first thing that jumps out to me is how
good Isaac Okoro and Austin Wiley have been. Both are the top two in individual
wins and near the bottom in individual losses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stat is best used on a season to season basis because it is heavily
dependent on the other players playing around a single player and the overall
success of the team that year. Because of that, I went on to come up with my own
stat to better assess players from year to year and I’m tentatively calling in
win contribution and loss contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;win-loss-contribution-explained&quot;&gt;Win (Loss) Contribution Explained&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My concept of individual win contribution and loss contribution is simply the
individual wins (losses) divided by the team wins (losses) for that season. In
my mind, I expected this to highlight good players on bad teams, and the data
for the Bruce Pearl era seems to support that, as you’ll see eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re familiar with NBA advanced stats, this probably sounds very familiar
to Win Shares. Win Shares are also pretty complicated, but if you’re interested,
they’re explained fairly well
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.basketball-reference.com/about/ws.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I do not calculate Win Shares if mainly because they (like other
advanced NBA stats) rely on a value for league averages in a few key stats.
Because the NBA is a 30 team league, averages are pretty readily available. If I
was using this for college stats, I could use an SEC average or an entire NCAA
average, but I don’t think that is very practical and would have a lot more
caveats due to unbalanced schedules and the parity of team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, win contributions and loss contributions are my way of showing these
same ideas just in the context of Auburn basketball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;win-contributions-for-the-bruce-pearl-era&quot;&gt;Win Contributions for the Bruce Pearl Era&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I mentioned above, win contribution tends to be a good stat for accounting
for good players on bad teams as shown by KT Harrell having the highest win
contribution in the Bruce Pearl era. It also is another way of looking at the
“best” player on a certain team, but this isn’t always accurate because
typically the better players also contribute a lot more and are therefore going
to also have more individual losses associated with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are the top 15 players by win contribution for the entire Bruce Pearl era,
plus the final year of Tony Barbee’s tenure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-1-31/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Top 15 Win Contributions over the 2013-2020 seasons&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Top 15 win
contribution percentages from 2013-2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the 2013–2014 and 2015–2016 seasons were so bad that three and four
different players respectively managed to make the top 15 in this list because
no matter how many individual wins they had, dividing by 14 and 11 is going to
lead to a high percentage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dominance of the big three (Chuma Okeke, Jared Harper, Bryce Brown) from
2018–2019 is also fairly evident because they still managed to all make this
list despite the team winning 30 games that season. This stat would also
probably be even more impressive for Chuma since he missed 2 of the games that
are still counted against him in win contribution and games responsible for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also of note, Isaac Okoro is on pace to match Chuma Okeke and stay well under 1
individual loss for the season, which is not something that many players that
play significant minutes can say. TJ Lang and Jordon Granger, the only other
players to have less than 1 individual loss for the season played 62.0% and
53.5% of team minutes in 2015–2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this post sparks some interest in others and does a good enough job of
explaining the basis for the stat for those that were confused when I mentioned
in originally. I also plan to start keeping tabs on this more as the season
progresses and will certainly look back at where Isaac Okoro can sit on this
least by the end of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first post of me explaining some of the more involved stats I
calculate and Tweet about, but if you have any others in the past or future that
you have questions about, let me know and I might dedicate a full post to them
as well. I also plan on doing more visual analysis in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading, and hopefully my stupid obsession with numbers isn’t too
boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War Eagle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Varner</name></author><category term="Auburn" /><category term="Stats" /><summary type="html">So the idea/reason for this post goes back to a few tweets I had earlier this month about the individual win-loss records for Auburn basketball players so far this season:</summary></entry></feed>